I'm doing it's like that no I'm gonna
jump okay recording now item thanks for
making time Thank You Daniel
over to you
you want me to go just go ahead okay so
I should introduce myself obviously to
begin with okay my name is Tom Goro and
and the president of the global coral
reef Alliance and I'm also chief
scientist of new regeneration SL among
other things I'm I'm a scientist I'm a
bio geochemist I mainly work on
ecosystem restoration in the context of
climate change were entrusted
fundamentally and we're generating all
the world's ecosystems in order to
regenerate their ecosystem services
including the regulation of climate
temperature atmospheric composition co2
in the atmosphere in particular and as
you know through the development of
industrial technology in the last few
hundred years we've created a situation
where we have destroyed half of the
biosphere there used to be twice as much
biomass in the world roughly as there is
now and that's gone and most of that
carbon that was sitting there in forests
and has disappeared is turned into co2
for soil carbon that is underneath that
that sense probably something like five
or ten times more than what is in the
biomass themselves it's a huge carbon
store and every place that we have
transformed the land from forest into
agriculture into pasture or grazing or
into any kind of human development towns
cities etc etc we have lost at least
half of the carbon that was in the soil
that's much bigger than what was in the
biomass so in destabilizing the system
would make the climate change situation
worse but at the same time we destroyed
their capability of what only living
organisms really do effective just to
pull co2 out of the atmosphere stored in
trees and then down into the ground
which is really the long-term storage so
that's a fundamental ecosystem service
the biosphere regulates our climate it
regulates availability of water
regulates the amount of food we have and
so we've really crippled ourselves in
destroying it and part of our view
by regenerating ecosystems intelligently
in a way to maximize biomass and
maximize productivity and maximize
biodiversity we can reverse some of
these catastrophes that we have caused
and and the critical thing is from my
point of view is we have to stabilize
co2 of climate at safe levels because at
the moment we are on a path of runaway
global warming something a lot of people
don't understand that the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate
Change talks about being increases of
temperature or sea level in 5 10 15 20
years maybe 50 years or so because the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate
Change does not have a scientific
mandate it has a political mandate
politicians want to know what might
happen while they might be blamed or a
response will have to make decisions but
they don't want to know what's going to
happen a hundred years from now a
thousand years from now 10,000 years
from now now the fact is though that the
climate system has a built in time lag
of several thousand years when we
increased co2 in the atmosphere now the
response of temperature is going to be
thousands of years in the future it's
not immediate and that is because the
heat is being stored in the ocean it
takes 1,500 years for the ocean to turn
over the deep ocean is all that
refrigerator temperature until that
warms up we won't feel the full effect
of warming at the surface right now that
heat is disappearing into the deep sea
we're not feeling it if that he had been
accumulating at the surface of the earth
93 percent of the heat is vanishing into
the ocean but if it had been sitting
here at the surface the planet would
already be unlivable that's something
people don't understand now the IPCC
projections ignore more than 90 percent
of the impacts we know once but I'm
going to happen and that's face not on
models it's based on the real long-term
climate change data for the Antarctic
ice cores and deep sea corals and corals
and all that sort of things we know how
temperature co2 and sea level have
varied in the past they're good data
records and we use that to determine the
sensitivity
of global sea-level in global
temperature to co2 we find that they are
far more sensitive than the IPCC models
imply was and just to give an example
IPCC will tell us that for doubling of
co2 no actually for the present yeah but
people are talking about is increases of
temperature you know one or two or three
degrees Celsius and changes in sea level
amount derived about that but tens of
centimeters maybe a meter or so and
they're talk about that happening by the
end of the century my point is as these
are just the very beginnings of trends
if I'm going to accelerate and continue
going for thousands and thousands of
years and so I pieces and only considers
the very initial product doesn't
consider where we're going and the point
is that we are already on a route to
runaway climate change that will result
in melting all the ice caps now when we
look at the actual long-term climate
change data itself the real numbers what
we find is that for 400 parts per
million of co2 which we've passed
already several years ago without 416
but for 400 parts per million what the
climate change data shows us peak steady
state changes in global temperature
would be about 17 degrees Celsius warmer
than today and the cela would be about
23 meters higher than today let's
fulfill hunt ppm we're already well past
that and it's accelerating we're really
on a pop now that will ultimately result
in the melting of Greenland and
Antarctica and that's 17 meters of sea
level change that's where we're headed
right now we're on target to get that
way now that doesn't happen quickly
because even Greenland is going to take
three or four or five thousand years to
melt its melting at an incredible rate
but there's a lot of ice that happens
slowly so that this impact won't be in
our lifetime but we have guaranteed it's
going to happen to future generations so
what I'm trying to say is the situation
is far more terrifying that the public
on this
stand who the politicians would make a
want to hear about because in a sense
they only want to hear good news so that
basically cooked the books to get the
answer they want which is not the answer
that affects humanity or our planet so
my point is that you prevent that
inevitable catastrophe from a scientific
point of view our only real solution is
to reduce the amount of co2 into the
atmosphere maybe there's a lot of
proposals for expensive technological
solutions and we're proponents of is
what we call geo therapy which is
basically the regeneration of the
natural biological mechanisms that
regulate our planet's climate and
atmospheric composition that that's a
callback jira therapy which is basically
treating the earth as a sick patient
here at there's running a fever the
temperature is out of control what do
you what would you do as a doctor with
your patient to stabilize the
temperature and bring it down to a safe
level that's what we call geo therapy is
correcting the heals now that that has
two branches one is by oh gee if there
are be witches you subtly kosa so the
other is what we call geoengineering
which is physical fixes like spring
sulfuric acid into space and giving
Europe an acid bath people are seriously
proposing that enormous looks putting
mirrors out in space there's solutions
that are enormous ly expensive unproven
and likely have side effects that are
worse than the problem they're kind of
soul so our focus is really on on
ecosystem regeneration on a global scale
to try to solve the problem now there
are many aspects of that and obviously
we're here to talk about seagrasses and
Posidonia mainly but i just want to put
this in the context of the larger global
issues of humanity as a whole faces and
if we don't solve this problem and we're
good to basically wipe out our species
and many others cockroaches will survive
bacteria was a survival world optimal
but but the planet will not be that
planet the human humans have evolved and
adapted to not
one that we could we could live in
securely at all who would love to have
another conversation to talk about soil
at some point but as he said like we're
focusing on on marine regeneration and
okay so just continue on here
essentially what what we have done from
our point of view is that um I've been
working for since the 1980s on a
technology that uses electricity to
regenerate marine ecosystems
it sounds very bizarre to people you
know everyone's afraid at all Christy
Frankenstein and getting electric shocks
and you know being killed and all that
so no one likes to talk about a twisting
water and of course naturally high
levels of electricity and in particular
alternating current but we get out of
the wall you know it's this alternating
60 cycles a second of course you know
you stick your finger in the electrics
all to hear you're gonna kill yourself
especially if you're wet and covered
with salt water that that can be deadly
stuff what we're talking here about
extremely low levels in terms of voltage
and current that are completely safe and
we're talk about direct current but you
get from a battery now the fact is is
you know we go into the water with a
battery on our watch we're going to walk
with underwater flashlights so we're not
afraid of it killing us okay I mean we
know that's that's that safe because the
amounts are very small and the human
body can tolerate that so we're dealing
with essentially our voltages and
currents that are down in that level
like what you would get from a battery
or from a solar panel and what we found
I have to really explain a bit of
history here I had a very close call
week he died more than ten years ago but
his name was wolf Hilbert's and he was
an architect who was originally from
Germany when he became a professor of
architecture in the United States and he
was interested in trying to produce
building materials from the sea so what
his point of view was is that a coral or
a snail can grow a shell or a skeleton
very precise architectural shape of the
dissolved minerals in seawater I mean
it's not collecting sword stuff is
taking dissolved room
silicate in it in a precise form and
shape and that doesn't happen naturally
you can watch the ocean for a million
years and isn't the limestone isn't
going to precipitate what what he found
was is that if he applied a small
current to the water you could grow
limestone rock out of you and I think
maybe it's easier if I show some
pictures to explain that process and
I'll discuss the applications to see
grouse so let me I'll try to share the
screen here and I'm going to show you
can you see this picture here yeah okay
so that is Wolfe filbert and he's making
a drawing on the bottom and so what he
found was that that's a bust of world
story that we have in Bali but this is
what we do we build structures out of
ordinary construction steel of any we
can make them any size or shape no steel
was the cheapest most common building
material in the world
as everyone knows and so we have a lot
of experience and bending it and
stretching it and welding it and we can
build any size or shape with steel
berries
now steel has a fatal flaw when you put
it in seawater it rusts very quickly so
when you put steel water it turns red
with iron oxide eventually it's gonna
crumble and fall apart
that's an evident so it's a very bad
construction material to use in the
ocean and in the ocean people make stuff
that looks like this figure out of
concrete steel bars inside of concrete
and what happens is to see what the
penetrates those made the concrete the
iron rusts when it rusts it expands that
cracks the concrete and it's crack the
water has even more access would
accelerate some rusting and eventually
the whole thing falls apart and every
reinforced concrete structure in the
ocean isn't collapsing in that sense I
mean it's inevitable that you see them
rust you see them crumble they have to
be torn down and rebuilt over and over
again so it's a poor material for that
purpose so we do something very
different we apply it's very small
trickle charge to the iron the right
polarity and then that completely
prevents rusting electrical current
itself prevents rusting
so in this case here and then what
happened something even more amazing not
only do we prevent rust put a little
more current in good then we actually
grow limestone rock this was the rough
that corals and snails and clams make
their shells from it's a natural
material it's all over the earth it was
formed
every almost all of this was formed by
living organisms and that's because
living organisms use their biochemical
energy to pull in calcium and carbonate
they use enzymes concentrate them and
precipitate them in a precise form
inside of the cell so that evolved over
billions of years to do that now but it
doesn't happen naturally but we find
that when we apply the current we grow
that rock right out of seawater we
precipitate it right out of the water
wouldn't happen naturally and so the
piece that you see here is a piece of
reinforcing bar steel bar about the size
of my finger and that is about a you
know about two years of growth with
mercurial of limestone now this is
limestone of course is something with
use of building materials from the days
of the pyramids you know limestone
doesn't dissolve yeah but this all very
slowly sort does dissolve an acid rain
okay you know you know a lot of the old
Roman monuments for instance are
dissolving because of acid rain that
that can be a part but that doesn't
happen in the ocean but we can as a
result grow limestone over steel in any
size you shape the material we grow
depends on how fast we grow it had to
good very good very slowly less than
about one to two centimeters a year as
in this picture that you see in front of
you we can produce material that's two
to three times harder than ordinary
concrete okay so it's a superior
material in that sense in terms of
scrape load-bearing strength that's you
know the amount of weight you put on it
before it cracks and crumbles um we can
good also very fast but then we get soft
material so our goal is to do it slowly
very slowly
now when Wolfe Hilbert's invented this
process
this method a he called it originally
mineral accretion that sounds like the
stuff you get in your cattle or in a
boiler but and he called it also
see-cret
or cement but I began working with them
soon after I heard about his work quite
by chance but he was asked at building
things in the ocean and maybe you could
grow corals on it and he invented this
process in 1976 in 1987 I heard about
him and I asked him to come to Jamaica
which is my home Island where I come
from so I asked him to come to Jamaica
and work with me
to try to grow corals so all we did is
he came down to Jamaica we built our
first structures and I the reefs that I
worked in in Jamaica I've known them
since I was a very small child and been
diving all my life from them
it used to be so beautiful and so full
of life and now they're dead and no we
killed them ourselves we human beings
and this we killed our roots in Jamaica
before global warming that's global
warming is the number one killer pools
right now but we kill them because we
didn't treat our sewage properly and
what happened is that weedy algae over
grew and killed the weeds because we saw
not only the most sensitive ecosystem of
all the temperature they're also most
sensibly nutrients and sediments but
every single thing we imagine so
whenever we developed the coastline and
we dumped our sewage in the water we cut
down the force and the soil washes into
the sea and global warming and and
putting pathogens into the water that
cause disease all of that wiping out our
reefs and soul into makeup at the site
that I worked in we were down to the
last few calls
everything was just massive weedy algae
slugging and killing everything or one
or two little corals here or there and
so I I transplanted some of these corals
on to some of these structures and
astonishing in three months they've
tripled in size and they were growing at
record rates in a place where the water
quality was so bad that they were dying
we got coral settling on these
structures at very high rates whether in
an area where there's no natural colon
so we realize we had something
biologically that was very interesting
so let me come back I mean
a little bit here to the physical
principles be sure more of this material
I called bio rock I invented that term
because mineral accretion didn't really
have an intuitive meaning to people to
sounds like that crud no so bio rock
gives the idea of a stone that grows
that's living and that's what we do it's
we're growing walk out of the sea and
these are a bunch of pieces that you see
here in this picture they're almost all
from the Maldives and they took they've
grown over by the one about a two-year
period in the Maldives with solar panels
and other left so a little trickle
current to them which we can provide
from any source and like that I just
mentioned that we use in our project
solar panels windmills
reduce tidal energy generate wave energy
generators but in most cases with us an
infrastructure to provide electricity to
shore
using the simplest waves to convert
ordinary alternating current electricity
no voltage direct current like what
you'd get from batteries otherwise you'd
have to keep you charging the battery
constantly you know as it grows down so
we often use electricity for that but we
can use any form of electricity and
obviously since global warming is the
number one killer of corals we try to
use clean sustainable energy renewable
energy whatever that is possible but it
isn't possible every going forward so
coming back to the materials I say this
is rock it's growing stone it's rock
hard the piece you see in the upper left
here and I don't know if you see my
arrow here on the screen that is one of
the first pieces that wolf Hilbert's
grew in Louisiana near the mouth the
Mississippi River but in the Gulf of
Mexico was about half seawater and half
freshwater
our process is based on the conductivity
of the water replying a small voltage so
they obviously flows through the water
and how much flows depends on how
conductive it is and how conductive it
is as function how salty this saltier it
is the more conductive it is the
Mediterranean is saltier than the
Atlantic Ocean so you would get
current to the same voltage in the
Mediterranean than you would in a place
like Louisiana which is half freshwater
so it doesn't work in freshwater this is
not conductive but it works in
intermediate so well this piece here in
the upper left was one of the first
structures wolf built and when he came
back three months later his PC cut out
was completely covered with oysters that
had grown to adult size and three months
it was astonishing so we realized there
was something there and we began then to
- you know when wolf started working
with me in Jamaica we began applying it
to growing organisms what we found was
as we could grow essentially all marine
organisms again at record rates we found
I'll show you some pictures of that a
little later but let me first stick to
the properties of the material this is a
piece of proving them all B's we look
we've cut it out but you see the steel
bars inside there's no rust on them the
completely protected this massive of
rock around them besides being the only
marine construction macule that's
growing and getting stronger with age
like a real coral reef it also is the
only marine construction material that
repairs itself here is a sum for a
series of photographs of a structure
that we built in Bali it was hit bad
boat a boat smashed into it it cracked
off the limestone on the outside and
exposed steel frames and those steel
frames had been the ocean for 11 years
and I give you a close that had no rust
some time series I'll give you some
close-ups here this is a after a year
the initial one okay well at the
beginning should be in this series I
don't I yes okay this is right after the
boat hit it and you can see the steel
bar was bent by the impact but it's no
rust on it in the ocean for 11 years a
year later that that looks that grew
back I mean that this is the area bare
steel but you see your new limestone
grew on it so these structures actually
are able to repair themselves and their
damage so they're really unique that
completely different than any other moon
construction material but you have to
think long term because going slowly
it's not like a car
we will building that you can pour this
thickness of concrete you know just pour
it and just wait for the set and you
have a building you know a few days
later when it's dry in our case we have
to grow it slowing it this way per year
and so to build something this big my
cake in Kenya Chris for 20 years and all
obviously people don't have the patience
that so the Wolf's idea as a
construction material is valid but it
didn't balance to slow people weren't
interested the fact is that in almost
any place that's on the coast we can
produce superior building material we
believe for less cost and a concrete
material would cost if you have to
import the cement Portland cement from
someplace else so in fact it is a good
building material who's not been
exploited and in a place like Majorca
for instance if you don't make your own
cement and you looked important in the
mainland our material would probably be
cheap so it has unique properties but
the fundamental thing that amazes us is
all these corals and things that grow
all over some of these little pieces we
put on but in most cases they're ones
that spontaneously that that's that's
you right after growth that's the bare
steel and then a year later you know so
it has pretty amazing properties I want
to hold on let me move through this a
little bit yes okay I'm going to go back
to the slide sorter I'm going to jump
here what we found was very briefly so
I've used slide sorter we found very
briefly was that all forms of marine
life are attracted to electrical and
this is something because the
fundamental basis of all life is
electricity people don't realize that
every cell of every living organism
through the lowest bacteria up make
their biochemical energy from about a
1/10 of a volt potential difference
between the outside of the cell me
inside and that means that electrical
current flows through the membrane of
the cell and bike was involved enzymes
that are able to trap that electrical
current and turn it into biochemical
energy but every form of life uses the
same mechanism goes back to what
course the last common Universal
ancestor billions of years ago the
identical mechanism so eltra c is the
basis of life and we basically
discovered as a way to increase
electrical field within the range that
stimulates organisms okay so if you add
you know to have no currently at the
kind in fact they grow faster of course
at some point it's too bad you start to
get negative effects so in the very low
range that their natural electrical
fields in fact workable founder's is
really that there are natural electrical
fields due to the magnetic field of the
earth and the fact that the ocean is an
electrical conductor and when an
electrical conductor moves with the
waves through a magnetic field sets up a
current and organisms have evolved to
utilize that current we were stimulating
that now normally what an organism has
to do is to spend half in some cases
more that bow chemical energy
maintaining the voltage gradient the
voltage gradient collapses the organism
dives it doesn't matter the seagrass or
a human being or a bacteria same
situation that voltage is not maintained
you run out of energy so the organ has
to spend a large part that energy
pumping electrons and protons and
maintaining that gradient that's energy
that's lost it's not available for
growth or reproduction or resisting
environmental stress in effect we're
giving them that energy for free and so
what we see is it but all forms of
marine life we get higher settlement and
actually attracted to the electrical
field because they're looking for we're
gonna for sites that have high wave
energy to live off that little
electrical field so we get they come and
settle spontaneously on our structure we
don't have to put them on the second
thing is that they grow faster it
depends on how much current they're
getting because i mentioned more current
more growth and then at some point you
to high so there's a broad range in
which they increase the growth rate and
we see that with everything that would
look measured we've measured with corals
with oysters
many different species not all of them
because you don't have the time or the
money to do that
but everything we've looked at grows
faster addition we get much higher
survival and we get much higher
resistance to severe environmental
stresses and for example with corals I
mentioned that global warming is a
number-one killer
high temperatures cause coral bleaching
and coral death and on corals are on bio
Rock we've survived bleaching when
everything around them dies it's
something that they have more metabolic
energy so they have more energy for
growth for resisting stress possibly for
reproduction but we don't know so it may
be the point is is the because of these
advantages we're able to keep whole
ecosystems alive when they would die
because severe temperatures events
severe stresses you know as we know are
getting worse and worse with global
climate change so we're able to keep
whole ecosystems alive when they would
die I'll show you some examples related
to seagrass in a minute but freeze with
corals we have we the only people keep
coral to live completion events so um in
addition because we're increasing the
growth rate and the settlement rate of
organisms so much we're able to
regenerate whole marine ecosystems and
biodiversity at record rates even in
places where there's no natural recovery
so places where all the reefs and
seagrass is dead we can grow them back
and so it's really remarkable properties
and they ate as far as we can see they
apply to all marine ecosystems so in
warm waters we grow coral reefs and cold
waters we grow easterlies we can grow
sea grasses anyplace in salt marshes and
mangroves and that that's what we want
to focus on here because obviously there
are corals around Majorca and the two
species of corals that occur in the
Mediterranean that are they don't build
wheat because they're mostly little
small ones isolated but we can grow
those too but in my York of course the
key interests of seagrass beds and there
were spectacular seagrass beds all
around my York and as in many places
there they're going back now sea grasses
destroyed about half the sea grasses in
the world it been dug up but
part of it is physical damage in a court
development and dredging and all that
but the main thing access is to curating
water quality seagrasses they need
shallow water with nutrients and light
now the nutrients get too high same
thing happens to them as happens with
coral reefs weedy algae take over over
Google and kill them if the water gets
too muddy they get smothered they don't
have light it can't grow so what we're
seeing in coastal development areas all
around the world it's a water quality
superior rating and the sea grasses are
dying even where we're not deliberately
destroying them but in many places we've
deliberately destroyed them for instance
I mean one example is in front of hotels
in the tropics
you have a beautiful beach you have
seagrass beds and from the seagrass beds
are the source of the sand and they
reduced the wave energy they protect the
shore but the first thing people do is
they dig them all up because they all
our guests don't want to stand and see
grass they want to stand on sand they
dig it all up and then they're surprised
of the beach disappears so just very
briefly Tom there the the seagrass
matter that is between formentera and
Eve it is actually one of the largest
living beings on earth
it's positano seanica and it's in terms
of extent because it's it's one
individual they just clone themselves as
they grow and it is and and all the
beautiful the beauty of the Balearic
Islands the attraction to the tourism
industry why people come here is because
we have these special turquoise waters
which are based on the white sands which
again go back to did you know how large
will sequester on North come in send you
some links yes we have to look sea class
is a beautiful ecosystem things that
almost all species of sea grasses
require sediment because what they do is
that the it's a flowering plant and it's
not actually true dress but it behaves
like a grass it has underground runners
so knows that the leaves are sticking
vertically up but
roots are growing through the sediment
and pretty much all sea grasses require
about five or ten centimeters or so of
sediments for the roots to proliferate
so without that sand or mud or something
else there they're unable to spread and
in your case you know you have large
flat areas covered with sand and that
allows what you say a clone its allows
one single lucky call it could spread
over huge areas so goodbye the roots
going through the sand okay with the
sands launched away all this they can't
grow and that's a major problem sea
grasses - is that extreme physical
events like hurricanes or like like
storm Gloria what that does is that
during digs up the whole mat of seagrass
with the roots and throws away and
washes away the sand and you get what we
called blowouts areas where it was
seagrass with some diesel cliff and the
whole thing has walked away and that
must have happened in around Majorca in
Gloria we don't seem to have any
information yet mapping what damage
occurred but definitely under those
conditions you do lose a lot of seagrass
in the long run it's deteriorating water
quality around ports and I imagine that
you see increase in port areas first
although there's a counterbalance and
that is that sea grasses need nutrients
and if the nutrients are low and the
sewage coming in the sea grass will grow
faster until the weeds take over so you
do in fact see faster growth of seagrass
around villages and small remote islands
and in clean areas because they're
living off the nutrients so synchronises
are a very important ecosystem and
wiping them out now there's another
point about sea grasses I mean sea
grasses stabilize the sediment because
of the roots they create a very rich
ecosystem that's essentially a nursery
ground for baby fish baby lobsters and
other marine organisms and a little
things are hiding between the blades so
that they don't get eaten by the bigger
fish and so they're an essential nursery
ground for many marine ecosystems that
then when they get bigger they move into
other habitats so they're very important
so there's many
reasons to reject there's another reason
- and that is that seagrasses along with
salt marshes and mangroves create a
marine soil and B grow the carbon that
they produce and the roots when that
deteriorates and builds up organic
carbon in the sediment and that is a
major sink of carbon globally as a
matter of fact as I mentioned there's
about perhaps 10 times more carbon in
the soil when there is in the atmosphere
or in the biomass numbers are little
uncertain some people use lower numbers
but I think the higher numbers are more
accurate every five to ten times more
you can argue about that but half of all
that's carbon soil is in wetlands
marshes from swamps and all that and
half of that is in marine wetlands sea
grasses salt marshes mangroves that
occupy less than one percent of your
service but they're holding a quarter of
the soil carbon so if we would generate
these ecosystems there are going to be
the most cost-effective carbon sinks so
we can imagine because you're going to
be able to bury the most carbon the
smallest here you could please cross so
that's another reason that would
generate sea glass yeah could you ask
you to last time we talked to you in
pointed out that in the initial growth
when the blade grows it actually
releases co2 in the process that
carbonate that is precipitated out
around the blade that the white flaky
bits don't actually create a net carbon
sink that it is only the biological
material in the marine soils together
the organic carbon that's buried in the
soil is not decomposed so basically when
it when the sea grass grows it's pulling
co2 in it's making organic matter if
that organic matter gets eaten or rocks
or decomposed turns back to co2 in the
atmosphere so it's only when they have
to get buried where it can't decompose
and sea grasses and salt marshes and
mangroves they build up organic carbon
some cases and the highest most
concentrated organic
Cardon of any soils in the world it
really can build it up and it's that
helps preserve it so that's the roots
and all that sort of thing but now that
the limestone itself is a little
different but people don't understand is
when when you make limestone the see
you're using what's called bicarbonate
that's a dissolved form and for every
atom of bicarbonate that you make into
calcium carbonate can precipitate out in
order to maintain the charge balance
that's a physical law you can't violate
that balance of charge like conservation
of energy and to maintain the pH because
the oceans are buffered system what
happens for each molecule of carbon that
you take out of the ocean put into
limestone you released one molecule co2
so in fact limestone deposition is a one
of the geological sources of co2 almost
everyone gets that back what they think
more reefs you have the more co2 you're
removing in fact it's adding but to put
that into perspective and all the reefs
in the world are releasing something
like less than 1% of what we're putting
in from fossil fuel emmissions so the
natural sources long-term source of co2
are limestone deep position outgassing
of co2 from volcanoes now the sink is
where that co2 then dissolves and
rainwater falls on the land dissolves
limestone then that co2 gets convert
into bicarbonate and goes into the ocean
so actually that's that's a sink is
limestone dissolution is actually carbon
sink limestone B position as a source
but it's small on a global scale
the real sink is bearing carbon now the
problem is that the ocean is a very
efficient ecosystem of carbons produces
essentially all even composed it doesn't
build up because it's extremely
efficient I mean the phytoplankton which
are the most productive they live a day
or two before they go back into co2 so
it's the oceans very inefficient of
storing except in marine wetlands marine
wetlands seagrass and salt marshes etc
mangroves are storing about half of
burying about half of all the carbon in
the ocean even though they all could
time much less than 1% of the area
in the deep ocean none of that carbon
survived at all decomposing goes back to
co2 unless you turn the ocean go dead
zone that's the only way to make the
ocean as a whole or carbon sink but
wetlands we can restore and store carbon
very easily we're going to have to do
that on a large scale the technology
we've developed because the Bhairav
method also greatly increases the growth
of seagrass salt marsh and mangroves
then we can accelerate that and I want
to show you really briefly what we've
done I mean this is all we've been
talking about general background and it
actually used a fair bit of time so
let's move on to what we do with sea
grasses in salt marshes now so let me
just ditch strings I don't know if your
people
remove the difficulty salt marshes and
sea grasses sea grasses grow below the
low-tide mark they're always in the
water they grew and said them the salt
marshes are similar types of you know
grass sea organisms and grasses in bed
in the real sense but they grow in
intertidal areas so they're exposed to
air some of the times and they're
underwater part of the time so they have
to have that exposure and you know being
underwater like that they're central to
life Manuel's only growing the
intertidal salt marsh grasses only
growing the intertidal so they form huge
swamps there are also huge carbon sinks
so they're very similar to seagrass yes
just briefly let you know that there is
the salt marsh on Majorca but it's dying
Isamu Farah in the north of the island
because it happens to be in the area
where there's also very intensive potato
farming and basically it's dying because
there's so many nitrates coming in from
yes what we'd like to look at that so
I'll work here I'm going to show you a
little bit of old um salt marshes and
sea grasses so let me begin with sea
grasses and I want to show you hold on
one second it's a seagrass section in
this presentation yes here so
is posted only oceanic a-- the same
species that you have in Majorca and
this is in new Puglia and southern italy
it's an experiment that we did I was
working with Raphael a back that Ella
who is he was the scientist for the
provincia di body in Puglia in southern
Italy and what we did in this case here
is that the pasta Don is disappearing
the Erika's like it is a mostly
Mediterranean variety of causes and so
we did here as we did the first pair up
Posidonia experiment or seagrass
experiment deliberate one and here we
did it as you see a diver in this
picture and there two patches here of
Macedonian growing what we've done is
these are patches that are you know
maybe half a meter a quarter square
meter in size I forget the exact shape
then we took you can see them it's a
mesh down here on the bottom so this is
a square mesh about you know centimeter
size spacing or so we put on the bottom
we applied an electrical charge and you
see where the arrow is here at the
bottom they're white that's white
because the limestone is precipitating
out on the meshes it meshes flat on the
bottom we did in these two places you
could put a few spartina roots and
shoots into them that's a easy to
transplant you can dig them up and
Transplant now in fact let me we say
something about that you people have
been actively transplanting seagrass and
salt marsh and mangrove they're easy to
plot you know you dig them out one place
you stick them in someplace else and
people have been doing that on a large
scale because all these ecosystems are
disappearing the problem with that is
almost all these restoration efforts
have failed and the reason they fail is
because heavy waves wash them away
before the roots can grow and be sorely
attached so I mean people make very big
clinto we planted a million sea grass
plants but you grow back here too late
are you lucky to find any surviving and
the other the other aspect is that if
you don't do what you're doing is to
find a way to increase the growth rate
then taking away from a healthy seagrass
meadow somewhere else
the things you plan somewhere else
you've actually done damage over there
the balance isn't actually that positive
that's correct you have to do better
than the original site so in this
particular case as you see here here's a
diver and what we did is this structures
of power these little meshes that was
very small I said we can do it any size
or shape and obviously we'd like to do
whole you know tens of square kilometers
but we're beginning on a little pilot
scale and this this project was powered
by a solar panel on land about a hundred
meters away and a little trickle charge
went into these structures we only did
this experience for three months but
what's important are two things first of
all the controls we had other pieces of
mesh you weren't getting out just and we
planted seagrass under they all died
they all died so that's exactly the
ecological damage you're saying you're
killing you're killing it
unfortunately we have to do that for
scientific purposes or we like to do
that as well as possible we have to have
a control otherwise won't believe us so
the controls all that these ones here
grew like tremendously and I'll show you
a few more pictures good point that's
important here is the bottom is not sad
this is rock we grew them on bare rock
something no one else has ever been able
to do before
okay because we had such political
growth and you see in the next picture a
close-up there and there's some of the
pasta Dona and here here's our mesh and
I think I think it was one centimeter
spacing I'd have to check that I think
that's it and if you look a little more
closely here we'll created a whole
little mini ecosystems you see the fish
swimming around this is a close-up of
the moon so after they they afterwards
so this is a mussel mussel settled in it
crabs it was shrimp all kinds of marine
worms and stuff so we created a whole
little mini ecosystem about this big and
it did very well
now this was a temporary experiment you
only did this for three months
unfortunately and we there those what
you know our permits were for so it
wasn't wasn't to actually do
restorations to do an experiment but it
was tremendously productive now I'm
gonna show I will show you a video
see us work in a minute but what we've
seen is that we're mainly not working in
C bus most of my work is coral
restoration but many of our coral reefs
have seen breasts around her under them
but so we've done many projects in
countries around the world where we go a
coral reef and we see the seagrass
growing more politically around and
under them so that that I'm show you one
video of that and the Bahamas in a
minute that's something we generally see
as we see the seagrass being taller and
greener around them now I'm going to
jump to salt marshes for a second when I
come back to sea grasses and this this
is a site in New York City
it's a Superfund toxic waste site and we
at that site this is this is our
shoreline I mean it's all toxic waste of
construction debris and all that that's
the beach and we've done is implanted
spartina alterniflora that's a salt
marsh an intertidal blast and obviously
were out there at low tide and model.i
tide was under water and with this area
was so poisonous this stuff couldn't
grow so we're growing these with solar
panels you see a solar panel here where
I'm moving the cursor and here's one of
our students here and she's measuring
the height this is a clump of sea grass
and toxic waste that we're growing and
she's measuring the height of them now
what we saw compared to the controls you
know control areas were responding
without electricity we found the sea
grass grew much taller
a blue greener it had tall it also had
many more stems for klompers as a root
mass and many more stems but we didn't
really count that we just measured the
height and so this is a gun what other
thing is we're able to grow these lower
in the intertidal than they normally put
bro so normally down the lower jerk
tidal there is a limit because they
don't get enough light or the wave
energy washes away and all that so we're
at six all the salt marshes are roading
natural salt lime roading because of sea
level rise when you look at the natural
salt marsh
most places to see that collapsing the
edges are falling into the sea and so
they're retreating and land of sea level
rise it's critical to extend them
seaward so what we're trying to do in
this experiment in New York City so here
we planted lower in the intertidal they
could grow and we've been doing that now
for about 1314 years and we started with
just ten plants and they proliferated
now we have hundreds of them going there
the controls all die every year what
happens is they die back in the winter
and they never come back in the spring
but ours just comes stronger and
stronger every year so we're able to
grow them tremendously here here's an
example of this Vartan again this is a
mesh that as I'd say 15 centimeters and
it's facing and it's very easy to do we
just lay the mesh down and charge it
appropriately and we're able to
regenerate them assured this is some
data from Sparta now the Reds are just
measuring the height this is in the
growing season for about three months or
so and you can see we measured the
height at the controls and then with a
little trickle at all Tristen a bit more
we're getting no increase in growth
above double under these conditions
possibly we could get it much higher we
had a higher more current at some point
you start to get negative effect so you
don't really know how high we could go
but what we're able to show is that
they're growing taller about twice as
fast in this growing season with under
these conditions but also we have many
more stems than the plants of Gleaner so
they're more more photosynthetic so we
we showed here that we could regenerate
Spartina
or salt marsh very effectively with just
trickle charge and solar panels and NC
glass so all right so I want to let me
jump now to something else now we're
trying to apply this to mangroves as
well we believe this is a general
mechanism that affects all forms of
marine life and mangroves fences I do
most of my work is in Indonesia and
Indonesia is the world's largest area of
seagrass and mangrove in the world and
by far the highest biodiversity of those
ecosystems such as the center of
diversity and amount
and they're destroying them they're
destroying them like every place else
they're cutting down the mangroves for
shrimp ponds a shrimp all died from
disease they abandon them and suddenly
where they used to be a kilometer of
mangrove altas on open water it's
causing massive erosion for instance and
all over Southeast Asia because half of
the areas of mangrove that had been
destroyed have been abandoned because
they were unusable so we're trying to
regenerate those mangroves and turn them
into carbon sinks and orangutan
sanctuaries and sustainable fuels
sources it's a long story that we don't
need to get into here so let me let me
get back to the sea grasses though but
as I say it's a general application to
all marine plants everything so I'm
going to show you I think a short video
here and this video is just a minute and
a half but this shows sea grasses the
Bahamas now in this case here I didn't
lay a mesh down flat
I actually took mesh I rolled it up into
sort of a double cylinder okay and that
way I was trying to create habitat for
corals and fish as well as for seagrass
Magnus will show you what what it looks
like here and this is a Abaco in the
Bahamas yeah it's just destroyed by the
hurricane devastated seagrass beds are
crucial habitats as fisheries for
there's no waste of this kind there no
structures for them and so they get
eaten by predators
this firewalk reef in a shallow sea
grass in the Bahamas has attracted huge
populations of fish hiding here in the
daytime and feed at night and vice versa
it's made from a single sheet of fencing
material that's been rolled up into a
double spiral it's been charged with six
volts and about 1 amp about 6 watts and
the few tiny fragments of calls calls
couldn't grow on this habitat because
too shallow and haunt for them and so
they're very few naturally broken
fragments of life called at Washington
storms were a transformer to feel them
and as you can see them grown quite
magnificent Leigh in addition the
seagrass inside this and around the
structure is quite green and growing
more tall seagrass beds worldwide are
being wiped out in there
Kalaa double catastrophe with byrock we
believe we could help restore seagrasses
and restore fisheries habitat of the
species that rely on these habitats
we've done work with sea grasses in the
Mediterranean who found the were able to
grow sea grasses on bare rock wherein
only couldn't grow the prolific root
growth and attraction of fish and
mussels and clams and a whole very
complex ecosystem that built up around
them so we believe that by rock is going
to be a crucial method for restoring
seagrass habitats and coastal fisheries
in the future I think the point here is
that what we see it's a very short
hearing of course but basically if you
look at the height of the sea craft a
bit smaller and be around the structure
under them this is something we've
noticed in Panama and other places as
well so we don't have measurements I
mean I say if this leaves no work in the
field with this planet
see what we can grow and but we can see
the impact I think very clearly that the
Haydn's waiver under and around these
structures and what we would like to do
was to do some work with people in my
you're interested in generating seagrass
so see if we could apply our methods to
it on on a large scale to be generated
consistently think we have a solution
that is it's obviously there's a cost
because you have to find the target
electricity that's a limitation of our
method but we can do that with folding
solar panels and it could be very large
could you say a little bit because
you've just um started working in Spain
quite extensively and you you're working
on a project and under Lucia and to
protect beaches and can you just tell a
little bit more about the background
about your work in Spain and and the
partners in it Coris permeable structure
the water goes through the breakwater
solid wall but it's in the sea or on the
shore cause the reflection
certain bounces off that concentrates
all
on that plane and then it washes away
all the sand in front but disappears and
then the sand underneath disappears
launches undred to get a whole London
and the whole structure eventually
collapses and breaks and falls apart and
we saw that in scrum gloria sent you
every seawall in Spain that was hit by
that storm caused erosion in front of it
the sand disappeared and in many cases
the sea wall itself was destroyed and
broken by the waves so so they don't
work I mean that's that's one thing that
but here in Spain people invested so
much money in trying to protect their
futures for tourism and the building
walls and then groins as Pagonis you
know all over the place and the fact is
almost all of them failed people realize
that now they're guests for it because
all these beaches have disappeared the
hotel's not that sand back before it
ones up in 80 million current show up
you know looking for 2 square meters for
their death there's no sound there so
they're pretty desperate but the point
is sea walls don't work they never have
worked every seawall that's ever been
built if it hasn't fallen down already
it's going to some at some point in the
future and it's a huge business now the
point is what they do is they destroy
the ecosystem in front of them and the
ecosystem service so we do something
very different a coral reef does not
work like a sea wall there's a coral
reef is full of holes like these
structures water goes through them it
loses energy by friction the more things
grow on it the more seagrass they're in
some more clams growing on it
mussels more surface areas and the more
they slow the waves down because the
waves are able to grow through they
don't destroy the structure and that
depth that's why every place is a coral
reef or an oyster with you grow Beach
behind it and you kill the coral reef or
the oyster reef the beach starts to wash
away so we do is essentially sweet gross
structures I mean this is an example
here in front of each's and what we've
done in eight different places in the
world as we have grown back severely
eroded beaches of record rates by were
generating the ecosystem in front of
and creating fisheries habitat I mean
you see on this picture how many fish
hang out in the structure they're
looking for a place to hide the seagrass
bed this is not very much I mean if
you're small and can hide behind the the
blades of the grass that's okay but for
a bigger fish you know if they can see
we thought we're creating habitat we
were generating the Fisher's we're
generating all the ecosystem services
they provide it we're protecting the
sand the beach from erosion and more
than that we're also generating new sand
because we're getting prolific growth of
organisms that produce and when they got
calcareous algae that have good algae
and bad algae the bad algae the fleshy
ones that all go and kill kill reefs but
the good ones are the ones that make
limestone we get prolific growth of them
on our structures too so what we're not
just protecting the shore actually
growing new said and in Indonesia we
have places where we've had black sand
beaches and we're producing so much new
limestone sand is now a white layer in
front of the black sand beach material
we produce oh so now I would say here in
Spain there's a tremendous erosion
people realize that the methods that
spent so much money on they failed they
didn't work and with the very beginnings
of a situation where extreme events I'm
going to be more frequent and more
severe in the future until we control
global warming on the global scale so we
have to be prepared for our failures our
failures at global environmental
management and so what we're trying to
do it in places here in Spain would be
to grow leaps like this they wouldn't be
corrilesa be muscled we voice Therese
whatever grows naturally in that habitat
will try to propagate the seagrass
underneath it like we do here and that
that would be the goal is in a sense to
think about these structures for
instances that assigned accumulates
under them in storms but if you had a
solid structure the waves would reflect
and they would scour the sand away
around them so this way we can in a
sense create sand bars in front of the
beaches and when the
a storm and sand washes away to be sit
on the sandbar and can feed back to the
beach in the calm season so we think
there's a lot of potential now what is
interesting is in those places only
regenerate at the beaches we've done
sort of constants up ten times less than
what a seawall would have cost the
seawall would have killed the ecosystem
services we regenerate them for a
fraction the price and grow the beach
back now we have in Indonesia we've
grown back each's in months record rates
you know several meters high hundreds of
meters long 20 or 30 meters wide and
done back at incredible rates so what
we're doing with blue regeneration which
is this new Spanish company just form
that on Friday last year we don't even
have our website up yet we'll post that
as quickly as we can look we'll get that
to you but the purpose of blue
regenerations mainly improve our
technology - for power systems now the
thing is we've been mostly doing very
small projects because there's no money
in marine ecosystem is no funding
community good system restorations not
something anyone any policymaker has
been taking seriously up to now this
sense you have volunteers out there
planting seagrass because they know it's
the right thing to do but there's no
systemic funding now so that's why we've
been doing small-scale part just like
this one I show you in the Bahamas I
built this thing in one day okay
let me ask you one question which you
would also be interesting for the New
York an example is that there's some
areas some of the larger Bay's around
the island where there's a high
concentration of hotels and basically
unfortunate Majorca still not up to
scratch with the way that they treat
domestic general switch and over maybe
eutrophication effects when algae blooms
in the summer which of course the
tourism industry is not happy about
because the tourists don't like green
seas they like blue seas in this kinda
like using this kind of technology if
you have a very high nutrient density
because of runoff would directly improve
the growth rate would that be beneficial
and could it help with the
eutrophication as well
well it depends on the ecosystem corals
are the most sensitive of all ecosystems
to high nutrients because they get over
going to kill by algae if the lowest
nuclear bubbles others are different
weekly most of the places where people
ask us to do projects are severely
eutrophic quite frankly in front of
hotels or dive shops and then kill their
own ecosystem they do to treat their
sewage this is a worldwide problem it's
not just in my Orkut if me
we see this stuff flowing into the water
every place the same content well our
projects I think about our projects
obviously is we will get the best
results in the cleanest waters but what
is interesting is we also get very
positive results in the dirtiest waters
were no other method works I mean that
that's really pretty important so yes I
mean the algae are a problem I mean in
the long run you have to clean up the
nutrient sources but we I mean you see
algae on this structure here this isn't
water that's 2 meters deep there's not
much of a tide there but the ants you
are not really a problem there I mean
what we find is that the we build up
large fish populations in fact that's
one thing everyone notices their
projects my goodness this year you know
you look around and there's hardly any
and and so the fish eat the algae you
might have building up populations of
fish eating algae and so they tend to
keep it under control in fact we're
creating a whole new food chain of
eating keywords fish just briefly if
you're done with the slides let's let's
stop screen sharing so we can see each
other yes okay sure let me stop here yes
the Tony font has joined us Tony is
there and he used to work for Greenpeace
International I was on the board he's
been a captain on the world wildlife WWF
solar boat and and he knows the marine
ecosystems around
Majorca and the Mediterranean much
better than I so Tony if you're there
could do you want to pop up your video
and and if you have any questions for
Tom I'd love to hear them
see don't need maybe he's away from the
squeak yes well anyway let's see if it
comes back but this has been super
helpful and I will share this with
people who are working in marine
protection here on the island and see
whether we can the conversation again of
marine regeneration is only starting
here but it's wonderful that do you now
have a Spanish based company in Spanish
based partners did you did you make sure
you also have a foundation and that is
supporting your work well I'm the person
in the font of the global coral reef
alliances have been around for about 30
years as a nonprofit organization based
in the United States we're used to
working with no funding especially in
this field but we work with partners all
around the world who have a problem and
they want help and they they want to try
using our methods so and that that we've
been doing small project but as I say
the magnitude of the problems are so
large that doing little demonstration
parts isn't really solving problems we
have to be doing this on a large scale
and that that's that involves
complications in terms of powering them
and so we have to provide electricity
but we providing authenticity over
square kilometers we need larger power
suppliers they need to be more efficient
even to be smart all that sort of thing
so the purpose of what we're doing here
in Spain it's been working with
engineers primarily and we're working to
try to develop much more efficient power
supplies for smart they feed data back
so we know how they're performing the
monitoring themselves and so forth and
so that would allow us to do very large
projects in my or not you know nonprofit
organization it's probably not the way
to go because at this point it's just
too small and impact so it allows us to
make demonstration projects like what I
showed you here with very little funds
but when we're talking about square
kilometers obviously we need a much more
serious organ trade and have you have
you got any data on because I was just
thinking of course the potential of
areas where this could be done we
be improved drastically the minute you
can grow posi dounia's slightly deeper
than it would naturally grow and grow
and I'm wondering with giving it that
extra help of the microcurrent that
helps reproduce faster and and so on
maybe you could find that you can
actually grow seagrass Meadows at a
slightly lower depth that's that's
probably true I mean we haven't had the
chance to experiment with that and
obviously I'm not going to make claims
that's something I haven't actually done
you know it's it's too easy to do but
but um the thing is in general we find
with most organs we're able to expand
their environmental tolerance range the
conditions that they would normally be
wiped out by extreme events in the case
of deep sea grass of course it's true
bidat events and block their light or
that they get buried in mud possibly to
grow so it's my view that we can expand
their range but until we demonstrate
that we can we're not going to claim
that but it's I don't think that's the
case I mean you might be able to extend
sea grass to the warmer colder waters
and they control that sort of thing so
yes there's a lot of possibility and
before before we wrap up and I would
like to give you the opportunity if I
any of the people who are working on
marine conservation and protection and
research in marine biology and ecology
here around the ballet Eric's that I I
will try to make this video accessible
too and and actually actively ask them
to comment on it
and you know it would be you opportunity
to ask them some questions of what you
would like to know about poly Eric's and
so we I can also add those questions to
the list so we can move the process
forward well I think I'm a tropical guy
and I'm almost always working in coral
reef so this is a bit exotic to me but
the thing is they're excellent marine
scientists here know these ecosystems
inside-out and we would like to try to
work with them to see if we can apply
our method to their situation obviously
we want we want to work with the best
people the ones who know their ecosystem
and the earth isn't inside out
and see if we can help absorb all this
here so eager to do that right now
because that's that's why I invited this
conversation because there is such an
enormous density of top sea grass and
and marine scientists on Majorca and in
the Balearic s--
that it's just an obvious place and they
I know that there are experiments in the
Bay of piensa that are funded by and
essa and that in media the Institute for
Advanced Studies of the Mediterranean
which is based in a small is here on the
island and have started but what they're
not doing is increasing the reproduction
rate of the growth rate and therefore
it's questionable whether it's there's
any real application for it because what
I'd say in every place we work obviously
would try to solve a local problem and
we can't every site is different it's
different wave energy forces history all
that sort of thing so we need to
understand the site and the problems
very well before we design something
that you know convict and and that's why
we want to work with local people who
know these ecosystems when the changes
they've seen inside out typically the
people come to us and they say you know
it used to be so wonderful here we have
almost now almost nothing left can you
help a usually they come to us when it's
almost all gone no when the conditions
have become so severe and so extreme
that you go with basket cases but at
anyway we'd have to come really I'd love
to come and see these sea grasses now
it's to quote me to go into the water
now I bet I mean I'd love to see me go
system can learn a lot more about them
and then I mean obviously the thing for
us to do is to dive in the water with
local people who know those areas and
then see what we could do each cycle is
different I mean actually they're the
specification is obviously relate to the
nature of the bottom the wave forces
that can get extreme forces that you
have to be ready to deal with not the
average conditions and then how you
power it that's a big issue I mean you
you have to either be near a place where
you can do for sure you might have
working solar panels it's a very
site-specific decisions how to do that
most effectively so that's what we one
of the problems with using DC lower
voltages over high distances that you
have such much as such loss in the
cables so you can only efficiently do it
and when it's close to shore that's
absolutely correct and that is precisely
the point of the technological
developments were making the CUDA
generations we're going to be building
systems that are more powerful more
efficient and capable of transmitting
over greater distances in some cases
what you have to do is transmit other
ways and then drop it down in low
voltage to the site but the transmission
losses that's what people use high
voltage DC you know transmission and
stepping down because that already
exists off the shelf
likes small units that you could sink
under well no we have we've built them
under my colleague here Thomas is
designing building such systems and the
purpose of this company at least is to
make them make them available on a large
scale but now we've been we've been
making them ourselves
these aren't commercially available
units Thomas has basically built them
himself and obviously there's a lot of
costs for prototypes and all that sort
of thing but that's that's the hurdle we
planted over come here and see the
efficiency on the spot excellent so I'll
stop the recording now and then we can
just wrap up and and then we see where
the same provocation and let me just add
one more thing I mean I'm going to be in
Spain probably until late next week I
don't know if there's a possibility to
come to my York I'm very happy to come
and meet with people learn more about
your ecosystems and your problems which
only a very small amount at this point
because I've never been there so I'd
like to learn from people but I'd like
to show them what we do show them these
pictures and we have more to but and
discuss how we could possibly work
together so if there's an opportunity to
come to my office it's not a lot of time
lead and of course I know everyone is
busy and not available on short notice
naturally but um then
it's a possibility come to my yacht
early next week say I'd be happy to come
and talk to people and make a
presentation not we try to build for the
future but what I will say is having
formed this company here in Madrid I
will be back for you great no I will do
my very best just to see whether we can
arrange something and yes on you next
week and visit to Spain that will well
thank you so much Daniel it's a pleasure
seeing you again and thank you so much
both for your work in the world and I
mean also I think that you two books are
just the bible's as we're now finally
moving into regeneration of the book on
soil ecosystems regeneration and on
marine ecosystems regeneration are going
to be classics for the recording